<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Kodierung des Aufsatzes zur Korrespondenz zwischen Arnold Schoenberg und der
               Universal-Edition</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Katharina Bleier</name>
               <resp>TEI Kodierung</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher><persName>Katharina Bleier</persName></publisher>
            <date when="2021-05-11">11.05.2021</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title level="a">The Correspondence between Arnold Schoenberg and Universal
                  Edition</title>
               <author>Katharina Bleier</author>
               <author>Therese Muxeneder</author>
               <title level="j"><title type="main">Archival Notes. Sources and Research from the
                     Institute of Music</title>, <title type="sub">No. 1 (2016): Musicians’
                     Correspondence and Interaction between Archives</title></title><editor>Paolo
                  Dal Molin</editor><publisher><orgName>Fondazione Giorgio
                  Cini</orgName></publisher><pubPlace>Venezia</pubPlace><biblScope n="12">twelve
                  pages</biblScope><date when="2016-11-03">2016-11-03</date><ref
                  target="http://onlinepublishing.cini.it/index.php/arno/article/view/39/146"
                  >onlinepublishing cini</ref></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <head>The Correspondence between <persName>Arnold Schoenberg</persName> and
                  <orgName>Universal Edition</orgName></head>
            <div>
               <cit>
                  <quote>[...] publishers and authors cannot remain friends in the long run.</quote>
                  <ref>Arnold Schönberg, Versuch eines Nachrufs für Her[t]zka, 1932 (Arnold
                     Schönberg Center, Vienna [T05.39])</ref>
               </cit>
               <p>With the exception of Mahler’s letters, of which only a few have survived owing to
                  considerable losses, and the Polish edition of Szymanowski’s correspondence, each
                  of these editions has only published a selection. The criteria used to select
                  correspondence for abridged editions are essentially based on the following
                  components:</p>
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>historical circumstances, e.g. a specific period in the composer’s
                     life;</item>
                  <item>author/recipient (for example, from the composer to the publisher and not
                     vice versa);</item>
                  <item>thematic, contextual focus:<list rend="numbered">
                        <label>a)</label>
                        <item>correspondence related to a specific work, or </item>
                        <label>b)</label>
                        <item>differing degrees of emphasis on aspects such as the genesis of the
                           works and the performance history, and also aesthetic, political and
                           biographical aspects as well as topics of cultural history. (This is
                           coupled with a reduction of letters with financial and legal concerns and
                           those relating to the production of scores.)</item>
                     </list></item>
               </list>
               <p> The editorial standards of the different editions also vary greatly –
                  rangingbetween those that are intended for a wide readership, and more highly
                  detailed descriptions.</p>
               <!--Tables-->
               <table rows="5" cols="2">
                  <head>TABLE 1.Correspondences between UE and composers published in book
                     form</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Karol Szymanowski ↔ UE </cell>
                     <cell role="data">Między kompozytorem a wydawcą. Korespondencja Karola
                        Szymanowskiego z Universal Edition, ed. by Teresa Chylińska, Kraków: Polskie
                        Wydawnictwo Muzyczne, 1978. (591 letters, complete)<lb/>Karol Szymanowski,
                        Briefwechsel mit der Universal Edition 1912–1937, ed. by Teresa Chylińska,
                        Wien: Universal Edition A.G., 1981. (Selection)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Leoš Janáček → UE</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Leoš Janáček, Briefe an die Universal Edition, ed. by Ernst
                        Hilmar, Tutzing: Hans Schneider, 1988. (350 letters, selection)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Kurt Weill ↔ UE </cell>
                     <cell role="data">Kurt Weill, Briefwechsel mit der Universal Edition, ed. by
                        Nils Grosch, Stuttgart, Weimar: J. B. Metzler, 2002. (207 letters,
                        selection)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Ernst Krenek ↔ UE</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Ernst Krenek, Briefwechsel mit der Universal Edition
                        (1921–1941), ed. by Claudia Maurer-Zenck, Köln, Weimar, Wien: Böhlau, 2010.
                        (1,298 letters, selection)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Gustav Mahler → UE</cell>
                     <cell role="data">stav Mahler, Briefe an seine Verleger, ed. by Franz
                        Willnauer, Wien: Universal Edition A.G., 2012. (34 letters, complete)</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>


               <div>
                  <head>ARNOLD SCHOENBERG’S PUBLISHERS AND CORRESPONDENCE WITH PUBLISHERS</head>
                  <p>The publishing houses connected with <persName>Schoenberg</persName> are
                     located in Austria, Germany, Denmark and the USA – with the exception of
                     Denmark, these are all countries in which the composer lived. While <orgName
                        type="acronym">UE</orgName> in Vienna and Schirmer in New York were
                        <persName>Schoenberg</persName>’s main publishers during his lifetime, after
                     his death Schott Verlag in Mainz and above all Belmont Music Publishers in Los
                     Angeles, which was founded by the composer’s widow, also played a significant
                     role.</p>

                  <p>Considering Arnold Schoenberg’s correspondence as a whole, we can see that he
                     wrote a large proportion of his letters to publishers. Of the roughly 24,000
                     letters known to us, correspondence with publishers constitutes about 12 per
                     cent of the total (TABLE 3).</p>
                  <table rows="3" cols="3">
                     <head>TABLE 3. Arnold Schoenberg’s correspondence with publishers</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Universal Edition, Vienna</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1500 letters</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1902–1951</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Verlag Dreililien, Berlin</cell>
                        <cell role="data">130 letters</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1903–1933</cell>
                     </row><row>
                        <cell role="label">Tischer &amp; Jagenberg, Cologne</cell>
                        <cell role="data">50 letters</cell>
                        <cell role="data">1911–1947</cell>
                     </row>
                     <!--weitere Tabelleneinträge detto-->
                  </table>
                  <p>However, only 5 per cent of these letters have been published, not including
                     the sections printed in the documentary volumes of the Arnold Schönberg
                     Complete Edition. This is an astonishing figure if one considers the relevance
                     of the letters’ contents for research concerning
                        <persName>Schoenberg</persName>, especially since they contain discussions
                     of enormously important issues pertaining to the works. About half of the
                     letters exchanged between Schoenberg and publishers involve <orgName
                        type="acronym">UE</orgName>.</p>
                  <p>Some highly relevant letters exchanged between <persName>Schoenberg</persName>
                     and <orgName type="acronym">UE</orgName>, as well as other printers, engravers
                     (Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, Geidel) and copyists have not yet been fully
                     researched. Another area to be explored is the correspondence between
                        <persName>Schoenberg</persName> and his son <persName>Georg</persName>, who
                     was employed as a copyist at <orgName type="acronym">UE</orgName> as of the
                     late 1920s, in addition to a number of students who were taken on temporarily
                     as editors at the publishing house, which could bring about a dramatic increase
                     in the number of letters to be edited. As has been mentioned, licences for the
                     works published by Verlag Dreililien in Berlin starting in 1903 were purchased
                     by <orgName type="acronym">UE</orgName> and thus, broadly speaking, these works
                     are to be considered <orgName type="acronym">UE</orgName> publications as well.
                     This qualification has consequences for the contents of the edition of the
                        <persName>Schoenberg</persName>–<orgName type="acronym">UE</orgName>
                     letters. As the Dreililien and <orgName type="acronym">UE</orgName>
                     correspondence overlaps in many places, we have decided to publish the letters
                     exchanged between <persName>Schoenberg</persName> and Verlag Dreililien
                     (represented by <persName>Max Marschalk</persName>) as an appendix to the
                     edition, which increases the total number from 1,500 to 1,630 letters. In the
                     spring of 1951, a few months before his death (on 13 July), <persName>Arnold
                        Schoenberg</persName> arranged for his entire correspondence – the originals
                     of letters written to him as well as his own letters in the form of drafts or
                     carbon copies – to be deposited at the Library of Congress in Washington D.C.
                     The comprehensive collection, comprising approximately 21,000 letters of
                     <!--Table--> correspondence and 35,000 written pages, provides biographical
                     documents aswell as information on Schoenberg’s artistic development. The
                     letters also attest to a half-century of cultural and intellectual history. </p>

                  <p>A not inconsiderable number of letters are currently considered missing; this
                     applies above all to the letters exchanged between
                        <persName>Schoenberg</persName> and <persName>Emil Hertzka</persName>, which
                     were stored privately by the publisher. After his death in 1932, the letters
                     remained in the possession of his widow <persName>Yella Hertzka</persName>, who
                     emigrated to England when the Nazis seized power in Austria. Parts of
                        <persName>Hertzka</persName>’s correspondence have been regarded as missing
                     ever since.4 To date, nothing is known about the whereabouts of his
                     correspondence with <persName>Schoenberg</persName>. For the correspondence
                     between 1909 and approximately 1920 we are therefore dependent on the letters
                     kept by <persName>Schoenberg</persName> himself; the sources improve from that
                     date onwards. After <persName>Emil Hertzka</persName>’s death and following
                        <persName>Schoenberg</persName>’s emigration to the USA he corresponded with
                        <persName>Hertzka</persName>’s successors <persName>Yella
                     Hertzka</persName>, <persName>Alfred Kalmus</persName>, <persName>Hans
                        Heinsheimer</persName> and <persName>Alfred Schlee</persName>.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Notes</head><bibl>Arnold  Schönberg, Versuch  eines  Nachrufs  für  Her[t]zka,  1932  (Arnold  Schönberg  Center,  Vienna [T05.39]). 2      In  2011  the  estate  of  Arnold  Schoenberg  was  inscribed  on  the  UNESCO  ‘Memory  of  the  World’ Register. 3http://www.mdw.ac.at/i14/?PageId=3668 [18 March 2015]. 4      A  small  section,  the  letters  exchanged  between  Gustav  Mahler  and  Hertzka  were  purchased  by Hans Moldenhauer after the war. See Gustav Mahler, Briefe an seine Verleger, ed. by Franz Willnauer, Wien: Universal Edition A.G., 2012, p. 62.
               </bibl>
            </div>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
